- Could the CIA really
track your heartbeat
from kilometers away?
On April 3rd, 2026,
Iranian forces shot down
an American fighter plane
just over Isfahan.
Inside were a pilot and
a weapon system officer,
and both ejected successfully.
The US forces located the pilot quickly
and rescued him only seven
hours after the crash,
but they couldn't rescue
the weapon system officer.
He landed elsewhere deep
within hostile territory.
And, worst of all, he was injured.
With the Iranian forces on his tail,
the officer needed to hide quickly,
so he disappeared into the mountains.
to rescue an aviator buried
deep behind enemy lines.
- Fortunately, the officer
had a rescue beacon
that could signal his location to the US.
The problem was that he
not only had to step out
of his hiding spot to transmit the signal,
Iran could potentially intercept
it and get to him first.
So he could only use the beacon sparingly.
With enemy forces getting
closer every hour,
how is the US going to
pinpoint his location
in the middle of a desert.
- [Gregor] A blind sweep of
the entire area could take days
or even weeks,
but, surprisingly, just
40 hours after the crash,
the US announced the officer was rescued.
- Still invisible to the
enemy, but not to the CIA.
- So how did they do it?
Well, according to a
New York Post article,
the CIA deployed a futuristic
device to rescue him.
Reportedly they were able
to detect the magnetic field
produced by his heartbeat
from kilometers away.
Such a device would have to
overcome the magnetic signatures
from other soldiers, vehicles,
and animals in the region,
let alone Earth's magnetic field.
It's like listening for
a murmur in a crowd.
So the technology was
appropriately called Ghost Murmur.
Immediately this kicked
off a media frenzy.
- Ghost Murmur.
- This is science fiction.
- Did you hear about what
the CIA tech that they have
called the Ghost Murmur.
- Called the Ghost Murmur.
- All of this sounds too good to be true,
and there seemed to be no other sources
beyond this New York Post article.
So we dug deep to find out
whether this supposed technology
really exists and what its limits are.
- I very rarely believe things
I read in the New York Post.
- Okay.
- I find it extremely
difficult to believe.
- Many of these researchers
in the NV diamond area,
are having to sign NDAs.
- The fact that the CIA is involved
in leveraging technologies
consistent with their
mission and their charter.
- So is Ghost Murmur fact or fiction?
There are two lines in
this New York Post article
that hint at what this device can be.
First, normally this signal is so weak
that it can only be measured
in a hospital setting
with sensors pressed
nearly against the chest,
the source said.
But advances in a field known
as quantum magnetometry,
specifically sensors built
around microscopic defects
in synthetic diamonds,
have apparently made it possible
to detect these signals at
dramatically greater distances.
We're gonna break this down bit by bit.
First, does the heart actually create
detectable magnetic fields?
Second, what are these synthetic diamonds
that could potentially detect them?
And third, is it all
possible at these distances?
Let's start with a heart.
Now, if you type heart magnetic
field into Google Images,
you will get a bunch of
questionable-looking graphs.
So is it a real thing?
Well, whenever current
flows through a conductor,
it generates a magnetic field around it.
And since our bodies run
on electrical impulses
traveling through neurons,
our tissues and organs generate
faint magnetic signals.
But because the heart muscles
fire in a coordinated way,
the magnetic field they produce is
the strongest in the body.
It's around 50 to 100 pico Teslas,
10 to 100 times more
than the next strongest
field produced by the brain.
But even then, this is
still a million times weaker
than Earth's magnetic field.
So it's no surprise that we only detected
the magnetic field of the heart in 1963.
It had to be done in a remote field
away from the magnetic noise
produced by lab equipment,
elevators, and cars.
And the setup had to be incredibly still.
Even the slightest vibration
of the detector would
corrupt the measurement,
not something that could
work on a helicopter
or a military drone.
But, pretty soon,
magnetometers got better.
By the 1970s,
we got superconducting
quantum interference devices,
or SQUIDs.
These magnetometers were
incredibly sensitive,
detecting fields as weak
as a few femto Tesla.
To no surprise,
the US military quickly
strapped these SQUIDs
to planes and helicopters,
and they tried to use them
to detect large magnetic signatures
like submarines in the ocean.
But the project never really picked up.
Nonetheless, SQUIDs also made it easier
to detect the heart's magnetic
field, but with a key caveat.
- They typically need to be operated
under a very tightly
controlled conditions,
often inside of shielded rooms.
They can't handle large dynamic
range of background fields
and electromagnetic interference.
- Future magnetometers offered solutions,
but they also had their own drawbacks.
There were always issues
with either shielding
or sensitivity or dynamic range
that made them impractical
for detecting heartbeats out in the field.
Until the 1990s when physicists started
looking into diamonds that
might eventually be able
to sense magnetic fields
while potentially getting
around the drawbacks.
- These new quantum magnetometers work
at room temperature operation,
and that's what's really
exciting about them.
They're also a solid state sensor,
which, you know, can be very
practical for some applications
and can be made into like a
more robust kind of sensor.
- These are the diamonds
mentioned in the New York Post article.
So how do they work?
Now, the overall coverage of the story is
actually very interesting
because this tech is
supposedly classified.
There's a lot of uncertainty
about whether what's being
reported is actually real.
And depending on which
outlet you see first,
you might arrive at completely
different conclusions.
For example, if you saw
this headline first,
you might be really impressed
with the technology,
but this one you'd be
a bit more skeptical,
and the last one might
not even make you care
about the tech.
So three headlines, three
completely different conclusions,
and that's where today's
sponsor Ground News comes in.
They're a website and an app
designed to make reading the news easier
and more data-driven.
Each day they round up stories
from thousands of outlets
all around the world
and give you a visual
breakdown of the story,
including its political
leaning, factuality rating,
and even ownership,
all backed by ratings
from three independent
media-monitoring organizations.
In case of this Ghost Murmur story,
you can see that it's been
reported on by 65 sources,
but the coverage is pretty lopsided.
So if you only get your news
from right-leaning outlets,
there's a chance you've seen the story.
But if you only get it from the left,
there's a chance you haven't.
And below that, you can also
see the factuality rating
and the ownerships of the sources.
They also have this blind spot feature,
which highlights stories
like the Ghosts Murmur one
that were under reported on
by either side of the political spectrum.
Staying up to date and well-informed
with accurate information has
almost become a full-time job.
And that's where Ground News's
approach is so valuable.
They make reading the news
more digestible and accessible,
and you can see all of the
information within moments,
not hours.
So if you, like us at Veritasium, care
about getting to the truth,
you can go to ground.news/ve
or scan this QR code
and our link will get you
40% off their vantage plan.
So I wanna thank Ground News
for sponsoring this part of the video,
and now let's go figure out
how those diamonds actually
detect magnetic fields.
Well, for something to
function as a magnetometer,
it needs to respond to a magnetic field
in a way that we can detect.
Now, a pure diamond is
just an ordered lattice
of carbon atoms,
so it doesn't react to magnetic
fields in a meaningful way.
But this changes
when you start adding
defects to the lattice.
You can replace one of the
carbon atoms in the lattice
with, say, a nitrogen.
And if you remove one of the
carbons next to it completely,
well, that creates a vacancy.
This defect is called a nitrogen
vacancy or an NV center.
And these NV centers
become particularly useful
when they trap two unpaired electrons.
That's because electrons have
this intrinsic property called spin.
A simple and flawed analogy is
that spin is kind of
like a tiny bar magnet
that gives electrons their
own magnetic signature
and it can point either up or down.
So when an electron is exposed
to an external magnetic field,
this magnetic signature
will either align itself
with the field or against it.
Also note that particles
that have no net spin
will not respond to an
external magnetic field.
Now, the two trapped electrons
can arrange their spins
in the following way.
They could both point up,
which would give you a
spin magnetic number of 1.
They could both point down
for a quantum number of -1,
or they could point in opposite directions
for a quantum number of 0.
We'll denote this spin magnetic
quantum number with ms,
and it essentially acts as a bar magnet
for the whole NV center.
And just like for individual electrons,
this bar magnet is also sensitive
to external magnetic fields.
So now that we've created a diamond
that responds to magnetic
fields, the challenge is,
how do we measure this
response to detect a heartbeat?
Okay, so I reached out to experts
to try and figure this out,
but basically out of the 20
or so emails that I sent,
I only got a few responses,
but then I got an impromptu
call from one of these experts
who said that many of these researchers
in the NV diamond area
are having to sign NDAs.
This is getting a lot more interesting.
But with how secretive everyone was being,
I had to use publicly available research.
And I think the key idea is to figure out
how diamonds respond to magnetic fields,
you have to use light.
When you shine light at an atom,
the atom can either absorb
the light or ignore it.
An absorbed photon of light
will excite an electron
within the atom to a higher energy level.
You can think of these energy
levels as discrete platforms
that the electrons can jump between,
just like in a video game.
All atoms of the same
element, for example, carbon,
have the same energy levels
when the atoms are far enough apart.
But when you bring them together,
like inside a diamond lattice,
their energy levels shift.
They come together to form a series
of closely spaced energy
levels or an energy band.
Now, an electron will
only ever absorb a photon
if the photon has enough energy
to move the electron across
the gap to a higher band.
This gap between the last
electron occupied band
and the first empty band above
it is called the band gap.
In a pure diamond, it's big.
It's around 5.5 electron volts,
which means that only ultraviolet
photons have enough energy
to excite the electrons.
All lower energy light,
including visible light,
will mostly be ignored by the
diamond and just pass through.
This is why a perfect pure
diamond is transparent.
It doesn't absorb any of the light,
but if you start adding defects,
they disrupt that organized lattice.
The defects unlock
different energy levels.
Secret platforms within this band gap
for nearby electrons to jump to.
A boron defect, for example,
creates a low energy level
at only 0.37 electron volts.
This is a platform that
electrons can jump to
by absorbing infrared or red light.
And with enough boron defects,
a significant amount of red
light gets absorbed this way.
The rest of the visible spectrum
mostly makes it through.
So without this red, the
diamond appears blue.
Similarly, a nitrogen
vacancy defect unlocks
other secret platforms.
And these can help us detect
how the NV center responds
to a magnetic field.
At first glance, it looks
like the nitrogen vacancy
generates a few unique levels,
and these are exclusive
to the two unpaired electrons
trapped within the defect.
But if you look closer at,
for example, the lowest level,
you'll notice that it actually contains
three closely spaced but
separate energy levels.
The second and third levels are
actually at the same height,
but will draw them separately.
And the fact that there are
three isn't a coincidence.
Remember, the NV center can
adopt one of three ms numbers,
0, -1, or 1,
depending on how the spins
of the two electrons inside are arranged.
If you think of the two
spins as bar magnets,
the most relaxed, lowest energy
way for them to sit is this,
one pointing up and the other down.
This is analogous to the ms = 0 state,
which is why it has the lowest energy.
Forcing both magnets to point
down together or up together,
like the ms = 1 or -1
states requires more energy.
They oppose you.
So these two states are
at an equal, slightly
higher energy sub level.
These differences are tiny.
Jumping from the 0 to
the +/-1 levels requires
only a small amount of energy.
A microwave photon of 10.4
centimeters will be enough.
Now, these secret energy platforms
of NV centers were mapped out by the '90s.
But for a long time,
no one thought to use
them as magnetometers.
- There was a decade before
the light bulb went on
for a bunch of us to think
about them as sensors.
It takes a mindset switch
to think differently.
And once you do, you realize,
"Oh my goodness, this could be useful."
- So let's apply a magnetic
field to this diamond
and see what happens.
If we slowly turn up the field strength,
you'll see that the +1 and -1
levels are starting to shift.
To understand why,
we can use a compass needle as an analogy.
Naturally, a compass
needle will align itself
with the magnetic field of the Earth.
And this is the lowest
energy relaxed state
that the needle can be in.
And it's analogous to the
behavior of the system
in the ms = -1 state,
which is why its energy
level drops slightly.
But if ms = 1, the system flips.
This would be like
taking an external magnet
and applying it to this compass needle,
flipping it 180 degrees.
And then if I'm careful
in retracting this magnet,
I can actually get the
needle to stay in this place.
And this is the highest
energy this needle can have
sitting in this unstable position.
Now if I tap it, it will actually go back.
It's possible, but it's
a higher energy state.
So the ms = 1 level slightly rises.
And if ms = 0, it doesn't
react to the field,
which is why this level hasn't changed.
Now, if you keep turning up
the magnetic field strength,
you'll notice that the levels
get further and further apart.
This phenomenon is
called Zeeman splitting.
It's described by a simple formula
that gives you a direct link
between the energy split
and the magnetic field strength.
So in the presence of a
periodic magnetic field
like that generated by the heart,
we would theoretically
see a rhythmic separation
of these lines.
And these two energy levels absorb light
at two different microwave wavelengths,
which change depending on
the strength of the field.
So what we can actually measure is
which microwave wavelengths
the diamond is absorbing.
When there's no magnetic field,
the levels are fused and
produce a single absorption line
at the wavelength of 10.4 centimeters.
But when there's an
external magnetic field,
they produce two separate
absorption lines.
Now, we've simplified it a bit,
but by measuring how spaced
apart these lines are,
you get the field strength.
This is how an NV diamond
magnetometer works.
Was the diamond magnetometer ever used
to detect a heartbeat?
- So what has been done
for sure is, you know,
for certain is detection
of magnetic fields generated by neurons.
Yeah, I mean, which is
to some extent connected
to the heartbeat question.
Neuron activity, to my knowledge,
has been first seen in 2015.
- Okay, well, that's,
wow, that's impressive.
So could it pick up a
heartbeat from kilometers away?
Well, in 2022, researchers were able
to pick up the magnetic
field of a rat's heart,
but it was done using a thoracotomy,
which means the rat's chest was open
and the diamond was less
than two millimeters away
from the heart.
Okay, but the human heart produces
a stronger magnetic field.
And the tech, the CIA might have deployed,
could be decades ahead of
what is publicly known.
You're former CIA operations officer
and you've worked in
the Middle East, right?
So what was your first
reaction to this news?
- Well, the fact that the CIA's involved
in leveraging technology is consistent
with their mission and their charter.
But I defer to smarter
people in engineering
and science like yourself
to figure out the exact
technique that might be used.
But the processes, of
course, are consistent
for what we've done.
- We can't say for sure
whether the CIA has this tech,
but we can use physics to estimate
how sensitive it would need to be.
Well, the strength of a
magnetic field falls off
with the cube of the
distance from the source.
So if the magnetic field of the heart
when measured at the
chest is 50 pico Tesla,
or 5 times 10 to the -11 Tesla,
well, then just 100 meters away,
this falls off by a factor of a billion
to 5 times 10 to the -20 Tesla.
And at 50 to 100 kilometers,
this could drop to as little
as 10 to the -30 Tesla.
- The most sensitive measurement ever made
at the frequencies that the
human heartbeat work at is
at the 10 to the -15 Tesla level.
And that's in a shielded room.
So you'd need a system
that is 15 orders of
magnitude more sensitive
than the superconducting
quantum interference devices
and 18 orders of magnitude more sensitive
than diamond NV sensors.
- 18 orders of magnitude is a
lot, sounds quite unfeasible.
- It's not like the hills of
Iran are devoid of animal life.
They also have heartbeats
and possibly larger hearts than humans.
- There's also the
magnetic field of the drone
or the helicopter the
device might be mounted on.
And, finally, there's the fact
that a magnetic field of 10
to the -30 Tesla is weaker
than a magnetic field an
electron will give you
a meter away.
- The New York Post is
notoriously a very good place
for amusing fiction.
- On the day before we saw this article,
we also saw an article
about how they had a technology
where it was a beeper.
and that was one way that
they were able to detect him.
And these are things that
we know about already.
We also know that there may well have been
other intelligence methods used,
but this isn't really necessary.
- And then that brings
you to the point of like,
why would they make this up?
- I think New York Post is
known to print a lot of stuff.
- I'm not a real fan of the credibility
of the press to report things,
having seen reality and then
seeing what the press reports.
- How about deception stories
and like false narratives
published by not only the CIA,
but other agencies?
Is this often the case?
- If you look historically,
the idea of fooling your enemy,
particularly when you have
some vulnerability to protect,
goes back thousands of years.
- During World War II,
German bombers frequently
attacked Britain at night.
And to retaliate, the British
would fly up to intercept
and somehow kept finding
these bombers in the dark
and would attack them.
Now, UK officials told the press
that the pilots were able to do this
because they ate a lot of carrots,
which was improving their vision at night.
But some experts believe
that this was actually a cover story
meant to distract the Germans
from the fact the British
installed radars on their planes.
- Is that where the idea
that carrots give you
good eyesight comes from?
- I think so.
I think this is the original,
yeah, the original myth.
- That is crazy.
- Yeah.
- But, okay, there's one
thing that still bothers me.
If this is likely fake,
then why is everyone saying no comment
and declining to talk?
There must be something here, you know?
- Well, these NV centers
and diamonds are also used
for quantum computing.
But the more interesting,
probably confidential
way they could be used is
as navigation devices.
The Earth's magnetic field
creates a unique pattern
all across the globe.
- Then to place an object into this map,
and if you know all of these perturbations
and in homogeneities,
you can infer where you are
without having any GPS reception anymore.
- With the rise of GPS spoofing
and jamming over the last couple of years,
that could be incredibly powerful.
So NV magnetometers do exist
with these synthetic diamonds,
and they do have potential
military applications.
It's just that detecting
heartbeats kilometers away
probably isn't one of them.
I wanna give a shout-out
to a great Scientific American article
on this story by Deni Béchard
that initially expressed
skepticism in Ghost Murmur
as a potential technology.
It's a great read and you check it out.